[Music]
welcome again everybody this is
yaservasif here from learn dental series
in this episode we will continue our
discussion in the topic of diagnosis and
treatment planning
and operative density
first of all i would like to declare
that i don't receive fees compensation
or relatives from the sales of any of
the products shown in this discussion or
in this presentation
and this presentation has not been
sponsored by any company agency or
organization and is prepared only for
educational purposes i would like also
to
remember you about this presentation is
copyright protected and could not be
transmitted by any electronic mechanical
or physical means without play or
permission of
the author okay
my
expected outcomes today is
to
correlate between the oral and dental
clinical findings and their proposed
treatment plan already in the previous
episodes we start to discuss our topic
in terms of part one patient assessment
and information gathering including
demographic data chief complain medical
history dental history and we clarified
in our discussion how to get these
information and what are the rational
and importance of getting such
information in designing your treatment
land and plan and managing
the patient problem
then
we go forward for clinical examination
and diagnosis starting with examination
of dental caries which is our
focus topic okay in this
chapter or in this presentation okay we
started with traditional techniques and
when we discussed the traditional
technique there is a lot of traditional
examination techniques including visual
examination tactile examination
radiographic discrimination and
limitations of each of these traditional
techniques we already started with
visual examination and
in visual examination we discovered that
there is a great limitations of what is
the translation of what you have seen in
your
brain and in your thoughts
and according to your knowledge and your
skill in operative density and in
cairo's management it this visual
examination differs subjectively from
operator to another okay and that's why
there was
too many attempts including
uh cares detection entities
developed by epidemiologists and the
cardiologists that they collect the
consensus
of carey's visual examination
to give it a score in a trial to
standardize
the subjectivity of visual examination
those indices
includes international cares detection
and assessment system
which is i see this as abbreviation
which uses visual service
characteristics to measure surface
changes and trying
to give it a reflection on the potential
histological dips of the curious lesion
and as we mentioned as a trial to
standardize the subjectivity of visual
examination between operator and
operator and from country to country and
from culture to culture
and a trial of that by collecting a huge
number of data along
a long time
okay that's why they
uh collect these data and trying to give
it a score okay
then comes the profile index which
focused on
the staging
the most severe levels of caries
diseases including bulb
involvement ulcers fistula and abscess
system
is in the cast which is the abbreviation
of cair's assessment spectrum and
treatment that includes staging curious
lesion both for early and more severe
cases or at more severe levels
then finally
the american dental association cares
classification system which describes
both cavitated and non-cavitated lesions
by clinical presentation without
reference to specific treatment approach
the treatment decision is yours you just
collect the data and according to the
case and according to the available
material you will decide
what is the suitable management of such
a case okay
also
the ada cares classification system
links clinical lesion presentation to
radiographic findings and to provide an
approach to identify
when possible
cares lesion activity over time okay let
us start with the first index which is
i see this
and the word is the abbreviation of
international cares detection and
assessment system then
the idea lies between two words
lies between
detection
and assessment remember that okay
we need a way for
scoring the detection and scoring the
assessment that's why
i see this is a clinical scoring system
that's used to detect and assist in that
cares okay it's generated to be used in
dental education
okay between students and instructors
okay to be used in clinical applications
okay especially when communicating
between different operators
okay and for different consultations to
ease the consultation just describe the
tools
in a scoring number okay then the next
consultant or the next operator could
imagine how the case started from the
number of the score you had written to
the patient file or to the patient chart
okay also it is used in researchers and
epidemiological studies
saves much more time when you describe
the lesion in number or unless core
rather rather than describing it in
written words okay this course reflects
too much information about your case the
scoring system can be used in coronal
surfaces and root surfaces and can be
applied for enamel cares dentine cares
non-cavitated and decapitated lesions to
detect and assess those lesions
also
icds measures the surface exchanges and
potential astrological dips of carious
lesion by relying on surface
characteristics okay
and then
it merges between the clinical findings
and the expected or proposed
histological depths of the lesion or
astrological involvement of the lesion
that will affect your clinical decision
in managing the case
so i see this
aim to gain better quality information
to make decision about appropriate
diagnosis prognosis and the clinical
management of dental care
at both the individual and public public
health level okay
all started in
2002 okay with i see this which at this
time it is icy does only but after
modification they
came back and determined it i see this
one because there will be a modification
modifications later on that's why it is
now termed with icds1 i see that this
one is
focusing on two components d components
component which is the detection and a
component which is the assessment method
at this time
this type of icds which is icds1
okay
it doesn't involve any
information about root cause or
previously
restored thief
it is only focusing in when the lesion
is cavitated or not active or not okay
that's it okay for primarily initiated
curious lesion not previously managed or
previously restored these doesn't
involve any information about the
service ability and of their spread
restorations or
their current careless status of the
tools also again doesn't include any
information about root cause the d
component in and icds stands for
detection of dental cares by
stage of the caries process which causes
the stages of careless process okay
starting from demineralization up to
aggressive curious nation involving the
teen and approaching the pulp okay
that's why it depends on that surface
topography is it the stagnation area
right bits and fisher carries or smooth
surface cares anatomy crown versus roots
okay
registration or sealant status that's
uh
the main idea okay to build or to modify
into icds2 but for i see this one it
depends only on the first two which are
stages of the various lesion and surface
tomography the assessment method
including stage and activity stage
either non-cavitated or cavitated and
the activity including active or
non-active region let us go for much
more details about icds1 okay i see this
one scores the visual examination of
carriers lesion into a scale from 0 to 6
okay
including only as we mentioned
before primary
coronal caries region either bits and
fissure or smooth surface lesions
active or non-active but previously
restored tools are not involved okay and
also rule cares
are not involved okay
scores
are very simple score 0 means sound no
curious activity at all score 1 this
means that the first visual is little
bit changes in enamel then comes score 2
it's distinct
obvious visual changes in enamel all of
these are without any breakdown of the
two surfaces it's just
visual changes okay then comes
score three
which we started to have a localized
name enamel
breakdown without clinical visual signs
of the internal involvement then starts
to be a little bit considered as
cavitated lesion
then comes
score four where the underlying dark
shadow from the deen starts to appear
which means that there is
a start of lateral extension alongside
in the
junction
five this connect cavity was visible in
team this also gravitated six extensive
disconnect cavity with visibility which
is much more aggressive or the most
aggressive
or invasive one those are clinical
pictures
showing
what you expect for each score score
zero okay
seems sound score one visual first
visual changes in enable score two code
two distance visual changes in enamel
code 3 localized enamel breakdown then
started a little bit cavitation without
clinical visual signs of the entire
involvement code for
underlying
dark
shadow from the team code 5 distinct
cavity with visibility and finally code
6 extensive testing cavity was visible
considering zakira's activity criteria
we have that code one two or three it
could be active or inactive
code four is properly active because
already you have a cavitation and you
started for dentine
going further in the depths of the team
okay
then
maybe for code five or six or score five
or score six
it may be this active or inactive
inactive means that
there is
a defensive action in a form of scalar
technique from the pulp okay which
make your carries okay by a way or
another arrested inactive one and limits
its spread okay
which is considered as afflicted rather
than infected thinking
okay
and
this layer will be solid enough
then
if it is scored or coded as one two or
three
if the surface of enamel is whitish
or yellowish opaque with loss of luster
if it feels rough when the tip of the
probe is moved
when the lesion is in a black stagnation
area like that of bits and fissure or
near the single and the approximate
surfaces it will lose a contact area
then it is
considered as
active leaking
okay
for codes one two or three if the
surface
of enamel is whitish brownish or black
okay
enamel is shiny and feel hard when the
tip of the probe is moved
surface lesion is typically located at
some distance from the gingival margin
and is not in a black stagnation area it
is considered as inactive or a requested
lesion that needs or may
be
managed by
remineralization or by altering the
patient habits or by bits and visual
sealant or may be managed
by
uh
preventive resin restoration or a
traumatic restorative treatment okay
that's why
it doesn't give you
a different decision making but it is
the decision making through
standardizing
the visual examination of your cares and
according to your collected data about
the careers risk assessment the general
oral hygiene the patient attitude the
patient diet analysis you could choose
between
remineralization and altering patient
habits up to
uh
managing it by preventive risk and
restoration or a traumatic restorative
treatment okay
you may wonder
how it could be a whitish reason and
inactive okay and how it could be a
whitish lesion and active okay
it's just a difference in your
inspection at what stage you are
inspecting your case okay
it may be from whitish to you
okay
in active lesion according to sustaining
all of them are a state of
demineralization as we discussed before
in white spot lesion and we
manage it by or in visual examination in
the last episode by
disappearing reappearing phenomena okay
both of them are demineralized
but both of them could be active and
could be inactive or arrested okay
that's why
if we have
wide spot lesion
which start to be
active or
assigned as active lesion
then
this wide spot lesion
is due to
demineralization of enamel that changing
the light reflection and light
transmitting
then these microbes or microprocessors
due to demineralization of enamel
starting to get yellowish
okay
and if it is
active lesion it will continue
to
dentine
without having enough time
to load or occupy these microprocessors
with more stains but when it is started
as a white spot lesion
okay
then
the procedure of carious lesions stopped
or the patient modifiers or a hygiene
okay or starting t
to
rearrange again
for
a
proper oral hygiene prophylactic measure
by himself or by any advice from any of
our colleagues and prevent the density
okay
then
still the pools are patent and still
receiving
stains that's why it becomes more
brownish and more dark without extension
of the carious lesion because carrier's
lesion is a stop but still the
microprocessor is open to receive
another discoloration this is the
explanation
for code 4
or score 4
always it's probably active four
score or code five or six you are now
indented if the cavity feels soft
overlay very on gentle probing
uh zen indeed then it is active if the
cavity may be showing a shiny dentine
that feels hard on gentle probing then
it is most probably inactive or arrested
again
this table
shows
what's meant by sound
okay
and what are the i see this dental term
and what either i see as detection score
or code early stages are for code one
and two established decay is
three and four severe decay is five and
six because you are now inside the team
and actively invading it
again
sorry
another table
showing the histological
definition or the histological depth of
the lesion link it to its clinical
appearance starting from
code 0 up to code 6 code 0 sound to
surface nucleus changes after air
driving for 5 seconds or hyperplasia
where erosion or other non-caries
phenomenons are not present then come
code one where the first visually
changes in enamel scene only after air
drying or
colored
change is are thin limited to
the confines of the bits and fishes area
and lesion dips was
in the
90 percent in the outer enamel without
only 10 percent in auntie
and so on
this will come in the major description
in the ada clears classification system
okay this is another repetition focusing
on
linking the
clinical
presentation of the lesion to the
proposed or expected
clinical histological tips
then
in 2009
[Music]
in a trial
to
uh and i tried to add
more perfection and more clinical
application to
i see this one i see this to okay
developed
okay
this is modified or coordinated by icds
coordinating committee okay
uh where it describes the coronal caves
and road cares okay
uh
according to their care is associated
with restoration and sealant which is
called cars okay
and i see this two we have
two digits in our code not one condition
okay
where is the first digit is related to
the condition of the tooth is it
restored or not
and with what type of restoration okay
it started from zero up to nine where
nine zeros is completely lost or missed
then comes the second digit which is the
normal range we discussed before
starting from 0 to 6 similar to that of
i seen as 1
okay
and there were a minor change
between the visual signs associated from
scoring from zero to six
okay
and also as we mentioned root cares is
involved that's why let us discuss the
first digit which is the new one first
digit that started from 0 up to 9 which
describe the condition of the tools
rather than the condition of the care is
various lesion it's itself
code 0 means that
the tooth is absolutely sound not seen
before
or restored before
that's why if you code that was as 0 0
that means that it is
absolutely sound
and if you coded as
0 1 that means that the rules is not
restored before not managed before not
treated before but once means that the
first visual changes in enamel as we
mentioned before from scoring from zero
to six okay
then comes digit one which is partial
sealant
2 full sealant digit 3 is restored with
two scalar restoration then if you
describe a twos by three zeros that
means that your restoration is surfacing
well it's a successful one that was
restored with direct tools colored
restoration or two-scale restoration and
at the same time there is no signs or
symptoms of a failed restoration or a
recurrent case at all okay then
successful composite resonance
restoration okay without any complaints
without any signs of recurrent carriers
will be scored as three zero three for
the type of restoration and zero for the
condition of the tools itself from the
keras progress point of view american
restoration is coded for stainless steel
crowns escorted five porcelain or gold
or porcelain fused to metal crowns or
veneers are coded six
lost or broke administration
are coded seven okay
and timber restoration is coded
eight and finally missed two's is coded
nine
but there is another breakdown under
nine which is the missing of our
zamasu's okay
if the truth is coded
nine zero
then the truth
is
missed
and 0 means that it is restored by
implant
but the cause of missing
is not due to cares
ok
then 9
means that you don't have a natural
tooth okay the truth is absolutely
missed
but if it is restored by implant
okay or it is restored by any prosthesis
you should ask about the cause of
extraction of the cause of missing the
teeth okay
then
nine zero means that the truth is missed
and missed due to non-carious causes or
reasons and restored with implant nine
one then that was restored by implant
okay but it was missed due to or
extracted due to aggressive caries
lesion okay if the truth is quoted
9 2 this means this means that it is
extracted due to an uncarious lesion and
there is a pontic
okay
and if the truth is
coded
9 3 that means that the source is
extracted eurocarious
reasoned and restored with a bondic okay
nine six
that means as the root surface cannot be
examined and this service is lost and
couldn't is excluded okay
nine seven
two is missing due to case and not
restored okay
nine eight
two is missing due to reasons other than
cares okay
nine nine it's uncorrupted twos at all
okay
this is the breakdown of code nine
then
if we have this exercise
we are trying to code this tools
according to
the icds2 coding system that was
restored with amalgam
and there is underlying dark shadow for
dentine with or without involvement of
enamel breakdown
okay then amalgam as being restored with
amalgam then it will take code for
and for the curious lesion okay
while the underlying dark shadow of
enamel appears then it will be coded
also four then the twos will be coded
for four when i communicate with any of
my colleagues okay or any of my police
will continue the treatment of my
patient okay just
write down i see that's two four four
he will translate this into the tools
was previously restored with amalgam and
there was a recurrent cares
okay showing the underlying dark shadow
of the team and you could estimate
what are the condition of the tooth
before treatment
another case
let us code tools number four six and
four seven according to icds2
okay
number 46 is completely understood
number 47 is restored with composite
result
tools number 46 unrestored then it will
be coded at zero then it shows the first
visual changes in enamel then comes code
one the second digit then this tools
which is four seven will be coded at
zero one
okay then
the second one is restored with
composite composite according to the
first digit of icds
it will be coded as 3
and at the same time
there is a distinct visual changes in
enamel not the first changes in enamel
around
the restoration it will be coded two
then the tools number four seven will be
coded as
three two
following the icds to coding system and
that's on okay
this
describes how easy
the communication
between
different
partners in the treatment of this case
either instructor and
interns instructor and students okay
between colleagues between different
operators if you would like to get a
consultation at higher level okay this
that circle describe the condition
exactly
then
when we considered the root cause okay
the root cause
it's called are very simple it's just
four chords e means that the surface
cannot be visualized directly then it is
excluded
then
the case having
a fair single condition
okay your roots are not exposed okay
your roots are covered
by healthy change partitions that's why
it is not curious and i could not
inspect it and it is
discord e
then comes the score 0 score 0 means
that the root surface does not show any
unusual discoloration
that distinguished okay at from
surrounding other root areas nor does it
have any surface defects at the level of
cement to enamel junction or root
surface then the root surface has a
natural contour but the only problem is
you have aboriginal problems that
exposed your root that's it it's a
matter of gingivalization without any
carious process that could be considered
then
comes code one there is a demarcated
area on the root surface
or at the cementum enamel junction okay
that is discolored but there is no
cavitation
okay
the loss of anatomical contour do not
exceed 0.5 millimeter
if it is present
then that means that the clinical
condition is showing a ginger recession
exposing to the root the roots started
to be damaged but it is a minimal damage
that does not exceed 0.5 millimeters
okay
then comes
co2 which is similar to code one but the
only difference is your damage or loss
of anatomical contours exceeds or equal
to 0.5 millimeters okay and it could be
measured by using periodontal graduated
probe for root cause activity we
discussed before in icds1 what is the
activity and how to measure it for one
two three okay code and for four which
is
mostly active and five and six which
would be active or inactive and we
discussed all the criteria for root
cause activity assessment okay we could
follow a similar
scheme okay
color
if it is active it seems to be yellow or
light brown inactive okay or arrested
one it is darkly stained okay perception
on probing
for active root care is it will be soft
or lavery in texture okay for inactive
at rest it is similarly to that of the
crown it will be hard picture okay
appearance is the same for active fruit
lesions it's mad okay uh for inactive
it's shiny picture for active root care
is its rough surface for inactive it is
a smooth surface cavitation active
lesion may be gravitated or uncavitated
but most probably in active lesion is
cavitated okay
appearance
okay for
active caries
root cares
closely adjacent to the crystal of the
gingival margin but for inactive more
distant from the gingival crest above to
near to that of the crown okay
in general for inactive arrested lesion
okay most commonly from my clinical
experience search for the clasp of your
partial denture okay this area may
receive a clasp okay which could be
modified by the patient pending or
something like that especially for
interim
acrylic partial dentures okay
may be the cause of this lesion and it
started as where at the cervical area
which is super opposed by cares that's
why it is mostly harvested okay
in another modification but it is
uncommon okay for
most of practitioners is the emma icds
what is mic does is a modified form of
icds one okay or in general it is a
modified uh form of icds
collecting the codes from zero to six to
make it just zero to four okay
linking the clinical appearance with
equivalent underlying lesion histology
okay it's called
deeper to histology
rather than clinical situation okay
it also correlates
the radiographic appearance okay and the
dips to enable
okay to enable and in appears in a
radiograph okay
it's not
too much clinically applied but it is
helpful in scoring the inclusion okay of
the carious lesion and the progress of
it okay would include it as a patient
note okay when you are following the
case for monitoring or for them to legal
purposes okay i started with
uh code zeros and the patient uh does
not follow the instructions that is why
it is transformed into code one and so
on okay
it's helpful in such cases in
writing nodes okay and following and
monitoring a case
okay
in m
icds or modified icds we have a clinical
appearance in code zero no or slight
change in enamel translucency after
dryness for more than five seconds
okay
and the proposed underlying histology is
no enamel
demineralization or just narrow surface
zone of opacity with a slight
demineralization
code one
[Music]
shows a little bit obesity or
discoloration from enamel just like that
of white spot lesion which is hardly
visible on our surface but
obviously visible after air drying for
five seconds or a little bit more okay
but still no cavitation or occlusal
smooth surface this proposed that
the demineralization extended
to the outer
half or the outer 50 percent of your
enamel then comes
code two
in code to enable opacity which is
widespread lesion or dry it starts to
get much more discolor
discolored okay starts to be grayish or
brownish discoloration okay which is
versatile without the need for air
dryness okay either in wet or in dry
condition because already it starts to
get stains from smoking from
beverages from foods and drinks okay and
like
and so on okay but still you don't have
clinically cavitated lesion okay you
couldn't detect a cavitated lesion okay
in such a case it is proposed that it is
involving the whole enamel surface or
reaching up to the
junction involving the inner 50 percent
of enamel
starting to go forward for the outer
third of inanimate that means that it
started to spread laterally along this
argentino in am junction then comes
code 3
which clinically appears as localized
enamel breakdown
okay
and it appears object or discolored
enamel plus or minus grace discoloration
or shadowing from the underlying tinting
and demineralization is starting to
involve the middle
up to the inner third of the gene at the
same case
we could note
another code which is called for which
is a gross cavitation
and exposing the underlying state
okay sorry discolor the enamel exposing
and underlying
the skeleton also okay then
it is a dangerous one which should alarm
you about the condition of the pulp that
your demineralization and cares process
starting
okay to invade the inner third of
argentine towards the pulp okay and this
is
the whole conclusion
okay of
the five k the five stages of m icds or
modified ics okay involving from or
starting from
code 0 up to code 4.
as we
mentioned before in our discussion
that mic das also correlate the
radiographic lesion dips okay to the
equivalent in icds radiographic rotation
it will be discussed in full details in
the coming episode okay
i'm sorry
which is started from e0 up to d3 e0
means means no demineralization no
reducing c at all in enamel okay
and two stages e1 e2 and in d1 d2 d3
according to 17 thirds okay
and a correlation between m i see this
and enamel lesion okay
e1 which involves or radiolucency appear
in the outer half enamel okay
it could be seen in mic dash codes zero
and one okay
e2 which involves the inner half of
enamel then it is coded by mic s1 14
lesion d1 is equivalent
to m icds where the demineralization and
radiolucency appears in the outer third
of enamel d2
which is coded by mic das 3 okay or
getting the holds read then
demineralization will be involving the
middle third of the team and
subsequently the radiolucency appeals to
reach the middle third of the team d3
involves the inner third of the team in
demineralization and training lucency
which is coded by m icds as for
this is a clinical photographs showing
different stages
and different appearance of
micdes where code one is just an
incipient wide spot lesion uh becomes
evident with dryness a co2 brown
non-cavitated fissure with underlying
gray discoloration of the occlusal
surface okay
mic dash coat 3 where small cavity is
just the detectable
with whitish and the brownish
discoloration on the occlusal surface
regardless you dry it or not the
conditioner is wet or dry and cold for
is a grossly cavitated lesion as appears
in this condition
the second index is pufa which is
the abbreviation of pulp ulcer fistula
and abscess
this index describes the faith or the
subsequences of
untreated carious lesion
okay
and it describes
the burden of untreated cavitated
curious lesion then
it is not
designed or assigned to detect the early
lesions but it is assigned to detect
what is the secular of untreated carious
lesion and and how dangerous that it is
mainly used to destruct the to describe
the overall condition
of your patient regarding his interest
okay and the available management in
this country or in this area to manage
dental cares okay then
this index
is used for assessing the presence of
oral condition resulting from untreated
advanced stages of cavitated caries
lesion okay
that's why
it is used mainly in low and
middle income
development countries okay or areas
where cavitations are not being treated
for various reasons and the commonly
used dmf
index could not detect okay why it is
missed okay
that's why
we are now detecting okay
uh a conditions beyond thinking
okay
and the code of this
uh condition okay uses
p
u f a b for the presence of palpable
involvement
u
for the presence of ulceration due to
roma f due to is
representing presence of fistula and a
is abscess the upper case letter is
referred for permanent ease while the
lowercase
letters or small letters representing
insiduous these okay
let us discuss in full details in the
coming photographs okay number one pulp
involvement where
there is an opening goes along the
chamber which is visible okay or cruelty
structure are destroyed massively
destroyed by keras then it started okay
after the codes of i see this okay it
started after passing the dentine okay
and starting to get much more oral
problems as a result of untreated
curious thief okay
then ulceration okay presence of
traumatic ulceration soft tissue tank or
mucosa or cheek caused by tooth or root
fragments okay
or fistula
a sinus tract
releasing bodies originating from an
abscess and an opening into the oral
cavity the presence of fistula
indicating the condition is chronic
because you're already evacuating your
bus okay
and finally abscess where and into
alveolar abscess is present okay
you could note from all of these
photographs that
the age of your patient is
teenagers
where there is a mixed indentation okay
and bad oral hygiene in absence of
proper treatment due to a cause or
another okay
then
comes the caste which is the cares
assessment spectrum and treatment
first
joins the three incidents and this is
sorry and this is with each other
and this is related to
the detection and the assessment of
carious lesion and incidence
continues after passing 17 and
considering the secular of untreated
curiously
then
they cast
okay that's why it is called spectra
because it have a broader spectrum
broader spectrum starting from sound
tools okay
following it up until it is extracted if
it is treated if it is untreated i'm
sorry okay
so
the case assessment spectrum and
treatment okay it
links and joins the three instances of
dmf icds2 and both
okay that's why it covers the two-tailed
dental caries spectrum from the initial
induction of careers lesion up to that
into angular abscess okay
it differs from common cares and this is
ingest
restore tools is considered as sound 12
as sound twos okay an expense of this
will functioning and the inexpense of
okay
it's serviceability clinical service
ability and
is
fair enough
that's why okay restored tools
is listed
as
third one
okay it's not listed like i see this if
it is scariest or after the zero one
which is
non-restore tools if you remember in
icdus ii
non-restored tooth is
scored zero
okay and the second digit from zero to
six describe its condition regarding
caires okay
then comes scores other scores after all
of these breakdowns of six breakdowns or
seven
seven from zero to six after all of
these breakdowns for uh
score zero
that describes the sound teeth but here
okay it's just one digit and considered
the restor tools as long as
it is clinically clinically
uh
successful okay it is considered as
sound one
okay
let us
go to examine these chords okay
code zero
okay it's a completely sound dose
no visible evidence of
curious lesions is present
good one it's a sealed tooth pits and
fissure either partially or completely
sealed there is a sealed material could
do it's a successful restorative truth
okay that's why it is considered as the
same as zero and one but the difference
is it has a restoration regardless the
type of frustration that's why it is a
cavity has been restored with an
indirect or direct restorative material
current hearing without any dignity and
careless lesion and no fistula no
abscess no recurrent cares no signs
of any restorative failure
then comes
okay enamel which is not restored but
starting
to show visual changes in enamel it's
called sri was cast okay a clear
carious related discoloration white or
brown is visible including localized
inaudible breakdown without
visual signs of dentine involved
regardless it is gravitated or not but
there is no visual signs science often
discoloration ardentine involvement at
work
then comes the team with two codes
called four for internal cares
related discoloration indenting since
the shadow of dentin started to appear
underlying
under under enamel okay the region
appears as shadows of the scalar than
the invisible through namin which may or
may not
show a localized breakdown regardless
the enamel is shown or not shown
breakdown but you have a shadow of
dentine this is code four okay then we
starting involvement of linkedin good
five there is actual cavitation in
routine but there is no expectation okay
of bulval involvement is present then
you may be either
in
the inner third or oh sorry the middle
third or the inner third but there is no
signs of bulban involvement either by
direct traumatic exposure uh sorry
carries exposure or indirectly affected
the pulp pathos due to careless process
okay
then comes code six and seven for
palpable involvement
the bulb is involved
okay
then your cavitation is reaching to the
bulb chamber
okay or maybe there is a root fragments
are present okay
if it is
aggressive up to having a fistula of
accuracy of our abscess and a bus
containing swelling
then it is called seven okay then it is
aggressive bulbal involvement due to
dental cares and there is a pulp and
periapical but also due to this case
if the truth is missed or removed due to
dental cares it is coded eight okay
if
the truth having any matching criteria
related to any other codes or this the
above categories then it is coded nine
like
uh the truth is missed due to roma of
the twos is unerupted okay it is not
fitting any of the above codes from zero
to eight okay
then it is coded as night
then finally comes
the ada american dental association
kerry's classification system
which describes most gravitated and
non-cavitated lesions okay by their
clinical presentation without reference
to a specific treatment approaches
it doesn't
advise you
with
a clinical
decision
because still you didn't evaluate the
care is risk
of the patient you don't have a carers
risk assessment
in combination with carers risk
assessment ada cares risk cares
classification system you classified
your case according to ada system okay
and you have your gears risk assessment
either by that of ada or by camera which
will be discussed in the next episode
then you have a full picture that you
could
build on it okay or depend on it to
design or assign your treatment plan and
your treatment decision that's why
this classification
does not refer or reference to a
specific treatment approach because the
picture is not completed as you don't
have the fierce risk assessment but it
links a clinical lesion presentation to
its radiographic finding okay and they
provide okay approaches to identify
when possible security is a serious
lesion activity along the time of your
kidney station okay that's why
the american dental
association cares classification system
scores each surface of dentition based
on its two surface which surface you
have either smooth or bits and fishes
prisons or absence of carious legion
sound or caries and at what level an
atomic site of origin it started from
silver cleansing our stagnation area
severity of the change estimation of the
lesion of the activity and radiographs
also should be available and considered
this gives you
a huge broad spectrum view about your
case
okay
in your assessment produce process okay
includes identification classification
of the presence of the lesion including
white spot lesion okay recent
restorations due to ferrous disease
cavitated lesions and radiolucences okay
putting into considerations that
radiographic extent
only an estimate
of the mineral loss described
of for from your case okay but not
neatly into the lesion this is an
important limitation of your radiograph
radiographs
describes radiolucency in basis of
mineral loss
not the actual histological picture of
the lesion
okay
the design of ada cares classification
system
aimed to facilitate measuring the
effectiveness of contemporary
commonly known or commonly seen cares
disease and what is your management
strategy in clinical practice as a
profession tries to continue to stream
toward improving overall patient health
through improved oral health okay
let us
review this chart designed by american
dental association and it's available
for free online okay you could get it
from the website of the ada organization
okay
as you see from the first column to the
left it describes a clinical
presentation
and described it in as another label to
simplify it if the case in such
condition containing infectedness or not
the appearance in case of occlusal
surface bits and fissures appearance in
more accessible surfaces which is a
smooth surface cavities and what is
expected radiographic notation of such a
case okay all of these i would like
remember you it's a huge data collection
okay and that you allowed work made by
american dental association including
the research work including
epidemiological researches including
cardiology researchers okay worldwide
first one is
is considered as sound
okay which is
there is no clinically detectable lesion
okay
dental heart tissues appears normal in
color translucency and gloss okay
no surface changes
adequately or adequately restored okay
then it would be
also
restored probably to be scored as zero
then
sound means that the original structure
or a sound and at the same time your
restoration is surfacing well without
any complications okay and the prognosis
of the case is
excellent okay that's why in such a case
if it is a sound to structure it will be
coded as zero for icds okay and this is
uh
the clinical picture of it in bits and
fisher and and smooth surface okay its
radiographic mutation will be e0 because
you have no translucency
then coming the clinical presentation as
initial which is termed initial it is
the earliest clinically detectable
lesion
compatible with mild demineralization
lesion limited to enamel
or to shallow demineralization of
cementum dentine mildest form are
detectable only okay it is visually
non-cavitated
by all means
and it is ranging between icds one two i
see that two okay both of them are
considered as initial okay for
radiographic notation this either a1
e2 or d1
then it is considered in ada cares
classification considering that initial
curse
demineralization of enamel up to it
spreads
to the interior junction okay and
starting to involving dentine so that it
appears as d1 in radiograph okay it is
considered as initial one
okay
initial means that all of these
is
require
requiring okay
an uninvasive treatment
starting from all of these needs
conservative non-invasive management
starting from modifying the patient
habits and improving the oral hygiene
remineralization of the surface okay
reinfiltration or sealing of the
demineralized enamel then comes
a preventive resin sorry bits and
fischer sealants and comes preventive
resin restorations it becomes automatic
restoration all of these up till now
does not require
a routinely
plex
cavity design
okay lincoln
the moderate one
okay the middle one there is
a visible sign
of enamel breakdown
and
moderate involvement of the team
okay then
you could see established early
cavitated or shallow cavitation or micro
cavitation which is
icd-3 and icds4 okay
it's
appearance as a radiolucency or a
radiographic notation it's
mostly d2
okay not exceeding d2
where also
you are
uh designing at this condition a cavity
preparation okay for management in
experience of uh you have uh occasion
risk evaluation is favorable okay but at
this condition
it is not an aggressive cutting also you
may change your design from amalgam to
bonded restoration to make a
conservative cavity your cutting is
limited to the lesion in expense of your
oral hygiene measures are fulfilled your
oral hygiene is excellent and this could
be gained according to the results of
your
careers risk assessment finally advanced
lesion where enamel is fully cavitated
and then deen is exposed okay the
internal lesion is
a severe demineralization
and appears to be deeper in the deen
okay
then it spread or disseminated okay
rapidly okay it is discovered late
and considered as cavitated deep
lesion okay in the deal
which coded by icds codes five
or maybe six okay and coded
by
a d3 radiographic mutation okay
and this
will need another management considering
the bulb and how to restore this
extensively damaged or badly broken down
teeth most probably your management will
be arranged between
bonded restoration or
indirectly on the restoration according
to the accessibility or avail or the
availability
sorry according to the accessibility to
reach it into the oral cavity and how we
could isolate it what are they meaning
to structure and another much more facts
this is another chart
describing
the
visual examination
of such different lesions okay according
to also the ada classification okay this
one is
sound where
described that was has no cares okay uh
even after training for dryness for five
seconds no hypoplasia no air no erosion
no other noncarious uh lesion even if it
is restored it is the illustration
performance is excellent okay and the
prognosis is good then comes the early
lesion showing the first visual changes
in enamel or disconnect visual changes
in enamel okay discoloration or
much more but it is not cavitated then
coming the moderate lesion group which
is a localized breakdown of enamel then
comes along the breakdown showing the
shadow of the team then coming
destructive breakdown or cavity visible
in enamel and in the input involving
only half
of the dentin then comes extensive
lesion into
dentin okay
two
evaluate
your
carious lesion activity again okay
considering the location of the lesion
okay
inactive or arrested one will be
in
area
not a black stagnation area
okay
while active lesion will be in a black
stagnation area like that of
bits and fischer lesion approximate
lesions and
gingival lesions okay
black over the lesion okay in a wristed
lesion it will not be visible okay not
thick nor is not sticky while in active
lesions it becomes thick and sticky okay
surface appearance for a wristed lesion
as we said before it will be shiny and
its color will be brown to black while
in active lesions it will be made or big
and loss of leicester its color will be
white to yellow okay tactile feelings
for arrested legion it will be smooth
hard enamel and argentine while for
active lesions it will be rough enamel
and soft layering indeed gingival
condition
if the lesion is located near to that of
the ginger there will be no inflammation
no bleeding on probing means that the
oral hygiene is much more better than
that for active lesion this is in case
of arthritis
and in active lesion mostly it is
inflamed grace uh inflamed and shown
bleeding on problems finally all of
these and this is
are away
or an atom
introduced by
a huge data collected by
epidemiologist and the cardiologist why
worldwide just to standardize
your visual
perception to carious lesion it needs
too much
uh practicing it needs too much training
to your eye okay
to
follow these charts okay and to follow
these scores okay by training your eyes
for this
many many times okay as we always say
that practice
makes perfect okay i think it will be
easy for you to visually examine dental
cares okay
those are the text
books i followed during preparing this
presentation if you would like to get
much more information okay please
don't hesitate to ask me and don't
feel free to ask me at any time as your
questions are welcomed just ask me by
commenting to this video
and i will reply to you as soon as
possible also you could contact me by my
contact or info okay and finally thank
you for assigning this time to listen uh
to me please don't forget to subscribe
to my channel and activate the
notification to get all the updates
thank you yes sir
[Music]
you